Guide to the Girls' High School collection ARC.128
Brooklyn Historical Society
Girls' High School collection
1890-1964
Brooklyn Historical Society
Girls' High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
ARC.128
2.6 Linear Feet in three manuscript boxes and one flat box.
The Girls' High School collection spans the period 1890 to 1964 and contains ephemera, documents, photographs and publications documenting school events and student activities.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Portions of accession 1985.054 were the gifts of Grace E. Beadman, 1937, and Sophie E. Rie, 1986. Accession 2006.031 was the gift of Marjorie Smeltzer-Stevenot, 2006. Blue and Gold issues for June 1919, January 1921, and June 1921 were gifts of the Winterthur Museum Library in 2017. Sources and dates of acquisition for remaining items in the collection are unknown.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series by type. Within each series, materials are arranged by type and/or chronologically.
Historical Note
Girls' High School was Brooklyn's first all-girls high school, opening in 1886 on Nostrand Avenue between Macon and Halsey Streets in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Bedford-Stuyvesant. The school's distinctive building, borrowing from both neo-Gothic and French Second Empire architectural styles and featuring a prominent clock tower, was designed by architect James W. Naughton and was deemed a New York City landmark in 1983.
The school's predecessor was the Central Grammar School, a coeducational institution that was established in downtown Brooklyn at Court and Livingston Streets in 1878. As Brooklyn's population grew, Central Grammar School became too small to accommodate the large number of new students, and the need for additional classroom facilities became apparent. Girls' High School was one of two public high schools established in response to this need, the other being Boys' High School, which opened in 1891 on Marcy Avenue in Bedford-Stuyvesant.
Although Girls' High School closed in 1964, it later merged with Boys' High School and reopened in 1976 under its new name, Boys and Girls High School, at 1700 Fulton Street. As of 2023, the school continues to operate at that location.
Sources:
Jackson, Kenneth T., John B. Manbeck, and the Citizens Committee for New York City. The Neighborhoods of Brooklyn. New Haven: Yale University Press, c1998.
Parker, Vernon. "On This Day in History: September 23: Boys' High School Designated Landmark." Brooklyn Daily Eagle, September 23, 2010. Accessed October 20, 2010, http://www.brooklyneagle.com/categories/category.php?id=38255.
Robbins, Michael W., and Wendy Palitz. Brooklyn: A State of Mind. New York: Workman Pub., 2000.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Boys' High School register and publications, 1892-1943 (ARC.123)
Brooklyn schools collection (CBHM.0006)
Scope and Contents
The Girls' High School collection spans the period 1890 to 1964 and contains ephemera, documents, photographs and publications documenting school events and student activities. Materials include programs for events; a collection of school songs; yearbooks; issues of the student-produced literary journal, Blue and Gold; issues of the school's newsletter, published under the titles The Chaser Fortnightly and The Fortnightly; and two volumes of poems written by students.
Separated Materials
In some cases, duplicate materials were discarded.
Programs (documents); Girls -- Education (Secondary) -- New York (State) -- New York; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Volumes (documents by form); Newsletters; Poems; Sheet music; Girls' schools -- New York (State) -- New York; Single-sex schools -- New York (State) -- New York; High school students -- New York (State) -- New York; Public Schools -- New York (State) -- New York; High school students' writings, American -- New York (State) -- New York; Student publications; Journals (periodicals); Student life and customs -- New York (State) -- New York; School yearbooks; Boys' High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Girls' High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Series 1: Ephemera
  - Class Day programs, 1890-1899 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Course of Study, 1890-1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Commencement programs, 1891-1898 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Commencement programs, 1898-1903 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Commencement programs, 1903-1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Commencement programs, 1934-1941 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Commencement ribbons, 1895-1903 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Event programs, 1897-1957 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Events include Shakespeare celebrations, Schiller centenary, class tree ceremony (1907), musical performances, theatrical productions, and a 1942 Red Cross bazaar.
  - Album of ephemera, 1902-1910 (Box 4)
    Event and commencement programs, tickets, and invitations; ribbons.
  - Collection of Songs of Horatio C. King, circa 1903 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Christmas materials, circa 1905-1940 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Mixed ephemera, circa 1908-1945 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Includes programs for excursions to Washington in 1933 and 1935, Loyal League materials, information on the Nelson J. Gates portrait, a commencement invitation and ticket, and an informational booklet circa 1940s.
  - Theater programs, 1910-1916 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Shakespeare celebration flyer, 1916 (Box 4)
  - Annual stunt contest programs, 1928-1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - William L. Felter memorial exercises, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series 2: Documents and photographs
  - Notes and documents on school history, circa 1890-1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Calvin Patterson correspondence, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Calvin Patterson memorial window, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Historical note
    Calvin Patterson was the second principal of Girls' High School. He died on January 28, 1902 and the following year then-principal William L. Felter appointed a committee to consider erecting a memorial to Patterson. These efforts resulted in the commission of a Tiffany stained glass window to be installed between rooms 116 and 117 at the school in Patterson's memory. The window depicted Alcuin and Charlemagne but unfortunately is no longer extant, having been destroyed by fire.
    Sources
    Michelle Cohen, Public Art for Public Schools (2009, p. 73).
    This folder contains a photograph and descriptions of the window, the report of the committee that commissioned the window, and related invoices, receipts, and correspondence, including from Tiffany Studios.
    Separated Materials
    The committee report and related invoices, receipts and correspondence were originally stored in a custom black leather portfolio with white silk endpapers. This portfolio was badly deteriorated and causing damage to the materials within it. The archivist discarded the portfolio but photocopied the cover engraved with the words "Calvin Patterson Memorial - Report of Committee" in gilt lettering.
  - Administrative documents, circa 1906-1962 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Lists of prominent graduates, circa 1940s (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Alumni correspondence, 1946-1964 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Images, circa 1890s-1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Three cabinet card portraits of young women circa 1890s, possibly students, two with names on verso: Jennie W. Jeuness and Marguerite T. Lee. One small painted portrait of Mrs. E.F. Pettengill, date unknown. Two copies of an image of the school library from the publication School Libraries: Planning and Equipping the School Library (1918).
  - Class photograph, 1919 (Box 4)
- Series 3: Publications
  Related Materials
  Additional Girls' High School yearbooks can be found in the Brooklyn schools collection (CBHM.0006).
  - The Triennial yearbook, 1913 (Box 4)
  - Blue and Gold magazine, 1917-1927 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
  - The Chaser Fortnightly, 1925 (Box 4)
  - The Fortnightly, 1926 (Box 4)
  - Rota Sapientiae, 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Annex Log, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Biology Observer, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Mathlete, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Test-Tube, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Blue and Gold yearbook, 1931-1932, 1948 (Box 3)